A Guide to the Jerdone Family Papers, 1762-1866
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Jerdone Family Papers, 1762-1866
Library of Virginia
21607
0.60 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Miriam Huxter, 9 July 1939.
Alternative Form
This collection is also available on Miscellaneous Reel 647.
Biographical/Historical Information
Francis Jerdone (1720/1-1771) arrived in Virginia from Jedburgh, Scotland about 1740 and established a mercantile firm in New Kent County. In 1752, he moved to Louisa County, Virginia, and built "Jerdone Castle." Jerdone married Sarah Macon (1731/2-1818) 10 February 1753. His son, Francis Jerdone, Jr. (1756-1841), inherited "Jerdone Castle," as well as lands and businesses in Louisa and New Kent Counties upon his father's death, but may have almost lost them during the American Revolution. Jerdone reputedly was a tory, but his mother was a friend of Martha Washington and his property was not confiscated. Jerdone maintained a business network with relatives and friends in New Kent and York Counties, Richmond, Virginia, and England. Jerdone married Mary "Polly" Byars 20 June 1799. Three of their sons, John (b. 1800), Francis (1802- 1874), and William (b. 1805) became planters in Spotsylvania, Orange, and New Kent Counties respectively.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1762-1866, of the Jerdone family of Louisa, New Kent, Orange and Spotsylvania Counties, Virginia, consisting mainly of correspondence to Francis Jerdone, Jr. (1756-1841), of Louisa County from his sons, relatives, friends, and business partners regarding personal, family, and business matters. Also includes personal and business correspondence to and from his sons John Jerdone (b. 1800) of Spotsylvania County, Francis Jerdone (1802-1874) of Orange County, and William Jerdone (b. 1805) of New Kent County. Also contains business accounts, receipts for business purchases, personal purchases, and tax payment, as well as a list of slaves for the Jerdones' New Kent County plantation. Also includes the account book of Francis Jerdone (1720/1-1771) of Louisa County which also contains the will of Patrick Belsches (d. 1764) and the inventory of the estate of Judy Belsches (d. 1768), both of Louisa County.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically, with the undated material, business records, and account book of Francis Jerdone located at end of collection.
Related Material
Jerdone Family Slave Record Book, 1761-1865 (LVA accession 20415)
Jerdone Family Bible Record, 1720-1841 (LVA accession 20519)
Jerdone Family Journal and Accounts, 1749-1755, 1836-1845, 1873 (LVA accession 21655)
Jerdone Family Journal, 1750-1760 (LVA accession 21656)
Francis Jerdone Balance Book, 1750-1787 (LVA accession 20939)
Francis Jerdone Papers, 1783-1822 (LVA accession 21466)
Francis Jerdone Memorandum Book, 1766-1767 (LVA accession 21659)
Jerdone Family Papers, 1753-1890, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary (Mss. 39.1 J47)
Contents List
- Letter. William Douglas, Providence Forge, to George [___], Louisa County, 30 August 1782, 1; 3 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. John Jerdone, Jedburgh, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 15 June 1784, 2; 3 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. Thomas Mitchell to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 31 October 1784, 3; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Divers, Albemarle County, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 21 June 1785, 4; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Divers, Charlottesville, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 18 February 1786, 5; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. William Douglas, Providence Forge, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 1 July 1789, 5; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 3 January [17]91, 7; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. J. [Malaskie?], Kingston, Jamaica, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 7 November 1791, 8; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. Alexander Macaulay, (Man?) Town, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 22 August 1792, 9; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Divers, Albemarle, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 16 October 1792, 10; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Weare Braikenridge, Ashton, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 9 May 1793, 11; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. William Douglass, Providence Forge, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 25 October 1793, 12; 3 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 7 July 1796, 13; 3 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. Turner Christian, Providence Forge, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 6 November 1796, 14; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. William DuVal, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, 22 February 1797, 15; 3 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 24 February 1797, 16; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. Edward Herndon, Spotsylvania, to Francis Jerdone, 5 April 1797, 17; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 24 February 1798, 18; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 3 March 1798, 19; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 25 April 1798, 20; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. Mitchell and Gairdner to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 9 May 1798, 21 (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 23 July 1798, 22; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Certification by Joseph Brock, Justice of the Peace, Spotsylvania County, 8 August 1798, 23; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Suit Papers. Sarah Jerdone, executrix of Francis Jerdone, against Robert Andrews et al., Chancery Court, Richmond City, 1799(?), 24; 2 items. 4 p., copies. (Folder 1)
- Letter. William DuVal, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 11 March 1799, 25; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 11 July [17]99, 26; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 18 September [17]99, 27; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner to [___], 12 December [17]99, 28; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 2 January 1800, 29; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 13 February 1800, 30; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 22 March 1800, 31; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 5 April 1800, 32; 3 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. Elizabeth Macaulay, York Town, to [___], 12 April 1800, 33; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 17 April 1800, 34; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 24 June 1800, 35; 1 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 31 July 1800, 36; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 16 August 1800, 37; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 29 November 1800, 38; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 4 February 1801, 39; 3 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 13 February 1801, 40; 2 p. (Folder 1)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 21 February 1801, 41; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. George Gairdner to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 2 March 1801, 42; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 28 March 1801, 43; 4 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 14 April 1801, 44; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. George Gairdner, Richmond, to [___], 28 April 1801, 45; 3 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. George Gairdner to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 11 May [1801?], 46; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. Corbin Griffin, York, to Francis Jerdone, Richmond, 20 May 1801, 47; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. George Divers, Albemarle County, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 27 May 1801, 48; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. George Gairdner to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 14 June 1801, 49; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. [___] Mitchell to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 15 December 1802, 50; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. Alexander Macaulay, York, to [Francis Jerdone], 5 May 1803, 51; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. Alexander Macaulay, York Town, to [Francis Jerdone], 5 July 1803, 52; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. Alexander Macaulay, Hampton, to [Francis Jerdone], 20 March 1804, 53; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. Alexander Macaulay, Hampton, to [Francis Jerdone], 2 June 1804, 54; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. Alexander Macaulay, Hampton, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 12 October 1804, 55; 3 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 2 August 1805, 56; 3 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 23 August 1805, 57; 3 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 16 September 1805, 58; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 14 December 1805, 59; 3 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 26 April 1806, 60; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 18 December 1807, 61; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. Turner Christian, South Wales, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 4(?) September 1808, 62; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. W. Douglass, New Kent, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 23 September 1808, 63; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. William T. Nivison, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 10 October 1808, 64; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 22 November 1808, 65; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. John Warden, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 2 October 1809, 66; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 10 November 1809, 67; 3 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 31 January 1810, 68; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. George Braikenridge, Bristol, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 16 May 1811, 69; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. John Warden, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 15 July 1811, 70; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. John Warden, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 16 August 1811, 71; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 15 January 1812, 72; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 1 February 1812, 73; 2 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 9 February 1812, 74; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. W. Douglass, Providence Forge, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 26 January 1815, 75; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 10 June 1815, 76; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 77; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. William Mitchell, Hanove[r?], to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 27 June 1816, 78; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. John Jerdone, Spotsylvania, to Francis Jerdone, Spotsylvania, 8 August 1816, 79; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. John Jerdone, Llangollen, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 15 June 1817, 80; 1 p. (Folder 2)
- Letter. William Mitchell, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 20 December 1817, 81; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. William Mitchell, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 16(?) January 1818, 82; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. G. Thompson, Hano[ver?] County, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 12 February 1818, 83; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone, Philadelphia, to Francis Jerdone, [Pottiesville?], 3 July 1818, 84; 3 p. (Folder 3)
- Order concerning the petition of Francis Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, 3 May 1819, 85; 1 p., copy. (Folder 3)
- Letter. W. Douglass to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 13 March 1820, 86; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. William Mitchell, Louisa, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 30 May 1820, 87; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. William Mitc[hell], Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 8 June 1820, 88; 3 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. George Divers, Farmington, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 1 January 1821, 89; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. W. Browne, Williamsburg, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 25 May 1823, 90; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John H. Christian, New Kent, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 3 September 1823, 91; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Edward Watkins, New Kent, to John Jerdone, Louisa County, 14 December 1824, 92; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Edward Watkins to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 25 April 1825, 93; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Edward Watkins, Providence Forge, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 28 October 1825, 94; 3 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 10 August 1826, 95; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. James Innes, Richmond, to [Fra]ncis Jerdone, [Louisa] County, 3 August 1827, 96; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 12 December 1827, 97; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 14 December 1828, 98; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, 14 December 1829, 99; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Sr., Louisa County, 17 January 1830, 100; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. J[ohn] Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, 19 February 1830, 101; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Sr., Louisa County, 24 September 1830, 102; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Sr., Louisa, 5 November 1830, 103; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Sr., Louisa, 10 November 1830, 104; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Sr., Louisa, 12 February 1831, 105; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Jojn Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Sr., Louisa, 29 March 1831, 106; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Sr., Louisa, 2 April 1831, 107; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Sr., Louisa, 23 January 1832, 108; 3 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Francis Jerdone to William Jerdone, New Kent, 25 December 1835, 109; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone to William Jerdone, Louisa, 30 July 1837, 110; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. F. Jerdone to William Jerdone, "Mount Sterling," [New Kent County], 6 November 1838, 111 (Folder 3)
- Letter. Thomas Christian to William Jorden (sic), 5 F[ebruary] 1839, 112; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. J[ohn] Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, to William Jerdone, "Mount Sterling," New Kent County, 18 April 1845, 113; 4 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone, Spotsylvania, to William Jerdone, Orange Courthouse, 26 July 1845, 114; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Richard Tucker, "Mount Sterling," [New Kent County], to William Jerdone, Louisa County, 19 September 1845, 115; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, to William Jerdone, "Mount Sterling," New Kent County, 11 February 1846, 116; 4 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, to William Jerdone, "Mount Sterling," New Kent County, 17 June 1846, 117; 3 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. J. F. Horan, Richmond, to William Jerdone, 20 June 1860, 118; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Francis Jerdone, Bloomsburg, to "Miss Buford," 29 November 1865, 119; 2 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Alexande Macaulay, Williamsburg, to Francis Jerdone, n.d., 120; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. John Jerdone to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, n.d., 121; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. James Scott to Francis Jerdone, Louisa, n.d., 122; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Letter. Z. Lewis to [___], n.d., 123; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Notice by Sarah Jerdone to James Dabney, [Louisa County?], n.d., 124; 1 p. (Folder 3)
- Jerdone Family Business Records, 1769-1771, 1773, 1783-1825, 1827-1832, 1836-1840, 1842-1844, 1846, 1847, 1860, 1861, 1866, undated, 125-207 (Folder 4-5)
- Francis Jerdone Account Book, 1762-1773, 1778, 208; 1 volume (50 p.); Jerdone was the executor of the estates of Patrick Belsches and Judy Belsches, his wife, whose wills were probated in Louisa County on 10 April 1764 and 14 March 1768, respectively. This volume consists mainly of records relevant to the these estates, in addition to several pages containing personal accounts. (Folder 5)